<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for congregationall government: or, A defence of the Assemblies petition, against Mr. John Saltmarsh. Wherein is plainly discovered, that in his reasons against the divine right of Presbytery, under pretence of opposing the Assemblies petition, he doth as much oppose the congregationall way, and goes about utterly to overthrow all church-government, ministery, baptisme, and all church-ordinances whatsoever; and wholly to subvert the authority of the civill magistrate in all matters of religion. And, the Assemblies petition vindicated from his exceptions, by principles common both to the Presbyterian and the congregationall way; there being nothing in that petition but what is agreeable to the principles of both wayes. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76198</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861447</idno>
  <idno type="VID">113583</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240898519</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E336_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200809</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861447</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99861447e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113583)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E336[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for congregationall government: or, A defence of the Assemblies petition, against Mr. John Saltmarsh. Wherein is plainly discovered, that in his reasons against the divine right of Presbytery, under pretence of opposing the Assemblies petition, he doth as much oppose the congregationall way, and goes about utterly to overthrow all church-government, ministery, baptisme, and all church-ordinances whatsoever; and wholly to subvert the authority of the civill magistrate in all matters of religion. And, the Assemblies petition vindicated from his exceptions, by principles common both to the Presbyterian and the congregationall way; there being nothing in that petition but what is agreeable to the principles of both wayes. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho: Vnderhill at the Bible in Woodstreet.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Baxter by Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Saltmarsh, John. The divine right of Presbyterie (Wing S478).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Saltmarsh, John, d. 1647. --  Divine right of Presbyterie.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113583:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113583:1"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR Congregationall Government: <hi>OR,</hi> A DEFENCE OF THE Assemblies Petition, AGAINST Mr. JOHN SALTMARSH.</p>
            <p>Wherein is Plainly discovered, that in his <hi>Reasons against the Divine Right of Presbytery,</hi> under pretence of opposing the <hi>Assemblies Petition,</hi> he doth as much oppose the Congregationall Way, and goes about utterly to overthrow all <hi>Church-Government, Ministery, Baptisme,</hi> and all <hi>Church-Ordinances</hi> whatsoever; and wholly to subvert the Authority of the <hi>Civill Magistrate</hi> in all matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>AND, The Assemblies Petition vindicated from his Exceptions, by principles common both to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian and the Congregationall Way; there being nothing in that Petition but what is agreeable to the Principles of both wayes.</p>
            <bibl>Phil. 3. 16.</bibl>
            <q>Whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the same Rule, let us mind the same thing.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Published according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho: Ʋnderhill</hi> at the Bible in Woodstreet. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113583:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113583:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Eeting with severall of your bookes abroad, and finding therein many things which you popose against the Presbyterians not to be so warily pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as might be wished; I cannot but wonder to see your grounds and arguments so laid, that they wound your friends of the Congregationall-way, as well as the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans whom you do oppose; and that so apparently that it can-be dissembled: And though it may be thought not seasonable for them who (with you) plead for Liberty, to oppose you in that plea, yet you must not think that they do in their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences joyn with you in the Arguments that you produce, but look upon them as being no lesse destructive to their way then to the way of the Presbyterians, and indeed to savour of such a spirit as is against all Church Government, Church Censures, Church Officers, Church Ordinances, even Baptism it self, and must needs think by the Arguments here produced, that you do not beleeve there is any constituted Church, or Ministry, or Ordinances in the word at all, or that any at all, either In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, or others should ever be baptized. Give me leave there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to examine your grounds you go on, least under pretence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>opposing the Assemblies Petition, you overthrow the very Foundations, which all, both of the Congregationall &amp; Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian way, and whoever maintain a visible Church and Ministry, are equally ingaged to maintain, and do unanimous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree in, though in other things there may be differences.</p>
            <p>You first make a furious assault upon the Ministry, that they are but <hi>pretended Presbyters</hi> because <hi>ordained by Bishops,</hi> p. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their <hi>Ordination is personall and successive,</hi> p. 2. Because <hi>not gifted as the Apostles and Primitive Elders were,</hi> p. 4. because <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derships then were infallible,</hi> &amp;c. p. 5. 6. and the same things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, p. 15. 16. 17. And this is the maine drift of your whole book.</p>
            <p>Sir, these are things which we must disclaim; principles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113583:3"/> that the Congregationall way can no more brook then the Presbyterian. It was a <hi>solemn profession before God and all the world,</hi> by the Brethren, the Authors of the Apologeticall Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, p. 6. that <hi>not any of them had any other thought, much lesse opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but that mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>titudes of the Assemblies and Parochiall Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of England were the true Churches and Body of Christ, and the Ministery thereof a true Ministery; much l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse did it ever enter into their hearts to judge them Antichristi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n;</hi> and this notwithstanding <hi>the defilements which did then cleave to the true wors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip of God, or the unwarranted power of Church-Governours exercised therein.</hi> And they alwayes disclaim that Tenent as Brownisme (which upon all occasions they professe against) of holding the Presbyterian Churches, or even the Parochiall Congregat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons of <hi>England,</hi> to be no true Churches, and their Ministery no true Ministery; And therefore cannot joyn with you either in this charge, or in the grounds. And Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> in his <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the Churches of Christ in New-England,</hi> p. 111. affirms the like, <hi>We cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> saith he, <hi>the Churches of England were rightly gathered, and planted according to the rule of the Gospel, &amp;c. so that all the work now is, not to make them Churches which were none before, but to reduce and restore them to their primitive Institution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your ground for it, <hi>because they received Ordination from Bishops, or from those ordained by Bishops,</hi> will not hold. For 1. many of the Ministers of the Congregationall way, were ordained by Bishops (and have not all of them disclaimed that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, though perhaps some have) Unlesse therefore you will deny all those to be true Ministers or Presbyters, because so ordained, you cannot urge this as a sufficient argument against the others, which may, notwithstanding such an ordination, be true Ministers. And your self, I suppose, being so ordained, will not think it any hindrance but that you may yet be a <hi>Preacher of the Gospel,</hi> as you stile your self; and (if there be any true Presbyters at all) a <hi>true Presbyter.</hi> 2. If this do not Hinder but that they may be true Presbyters; though it should not be enough to make them so, yet what more have your self to make you such, then what they have, or those of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall way who are not ordained anew? For if a Minister may be a true Minister meerly by inward gifts without any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113583:3"/> outward Call, what hinders, but they may be such, whom you cannot deny to be no way inferiour to your self either in gifts or graces? Or, if Election by a company of godly persons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting to choose or accept a person (so gifted) to be a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster to them, may serve without Ordination; no question but many godly Presbyterian Ministers, have had such Election, and generall approbation of the godly persons within their charge, to be Pastors to them.</p>
            <p>And for that great ado about proving a <hi>certain perpetuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall derivation of power</hi> from the Apostles, and so, <hi>through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Antichristian Church,</hi> without which you conceive they can be no true Ministers: Sir, you do by that as much oppose all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, as theirs. For if it be necessary to the essence of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister that there be such a successive derivation of Power, then it doth as much concern the Congregationall Ministers, and your self too, to make it out; and if it cannot be done, there can be no Ministers at all: If it be not necessarie, why is it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted on? they may be true Ministers notwithstanding that there be no such succession.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the same Argument we must reject our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme; for how will it appear that those who baptized us were themselves baptized, more then that these who ordained Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters are themselves ordained; unlesse we prove a succession of Baptisme in the Antichristian state: and if so, then must there be a <hi>Perpetuall visibility of a Church, a truth of Church Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, and ordinances of Jesus Christ in the Antichristian State,</hi> which is the great inconvenience you feared: If there be need of a perpetuall succession in the one, there is need in the other, and if it may be made out in the one, it may be made out in the other. And if your Argument be good against the one, it will be as good against the other.</p>
            <p>But if your meaning be, that there is therefore now no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery, Baptisme, Ordinances, because there hath not been a perpetuall lineall succession as you suppose, and that for the same reason there can be none for the time to come, for as much as we have no Commission now for persons unbaptized to baptize others, and therefore (as you say) <hi>if the succession be false and interrupted any where, it must needs be all false from such a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113583:4"/> point where the first interruption was made;</hi> I say: if this be your meaning, speak it out, that the world may have a full sight of that your new light; and that they cannot be Mr. <hi>Saltma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>shes</hi> Disciples, unlesse they will renounce, not their Ministery one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or Episcopall Ordination, but their Baptisme also, and all Church Ordinances, and that not onely for the present, but for ever hereafter, till we have a new Christ, or at least new A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles to restore it again.</p>
            <p>But you adde, their Ordination is <hi>Personall,</hi> and therefore must be successive, and their <hi>Power derived from a personall and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall succession,</hi> and your opinion is, that there must be <hi>no personal Ordination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, is not Baptisme personall, as well as Ordination, and therefore doth as much require a personall succession? 2. Is not the Ordination of Ministers in the Congregationall way as personall? yea in all wayes personall, as well as the Presbyterians, whom yet you would appear onely to oppose? Must there not be <hi>persons ordaining,</hi> and <hi>persons ordained?</hi> do not the Dissenting Brethren, in the 7. Propositions given in to the <note place="margin">See Asse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>blies Answ: to the Copy of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monst.</note> Assembly, affirm, that <hi>Church Officers must be designed to their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall offices by imposition of hands and prayer;</hi> and this they call <hi>Ordination.</hi> But 3. neither do those dissenting Brethren, nor those from whom they dissent, affirm as you charge them, that their <hi>power is derived from those that ordain them,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom Jesus Christ, who-ever the persons be by whom they be outwardly called. But it's like your meaning is, that there should be no outward calling at all, that one is no more a Minister then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, but as more or lesse gifted; and when you speak against making a <hi>distinction between Laity and Clergy,</hi> you mean, <hi>between Officers and others out of Office.</hi> Yet your self adde by and by, that <hi>men may be Saints, but not sent, or ministerially Saints; good men, but not good Presbyters,</hi> p. 2. 15. which you must mean either of <hi>Some,</hi> or of <hi>All;</hi> if of <hi>all,</hi> then is there no Ministery in the world at all, (which I beleeve is your meaning). If, of <hi>some</hi> onely, I ask what makes the difference between those that are Saints and Presbyters too, and those that are Saints but not Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? And when you have told me, I am confident, that those whom you censure as <hi>no true Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Ministers,</hi> will (at least
<pb facs="tcp:113583:4"/> many of them) plead as good evidence even by your own Rules, as your self can.</p>
            <p>You adde, pag. 16. <hi>Though Christs promise is enough to ground a perpetuity of Church and Christs presence, yet not of his promise made good to such particular men:</hi> We accept your grant, (that there shall therefore alwayes be a Church with which Christ will be present; you might have added, <hi>in his Ordinances;</hi> for it is such a presence Christ promiseth.) Your exception is frivolous; for if you intend, that therefore no particular men may plead that promise; you conclude as much against all Ministery and all Ordinances wheresoever or by whomsoever administred: Yea against the Covenant of grace and salvation by Christ, which is no more made to particular men, then the promises of Christs presence in his Ordinances; yet particular men (though their names be not written particularly in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) may apply the promises to themselves, and obtain (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the Papists objections to the contrary, upon that ground which you here pretend) a certainty of salvation.</p>
            <p>You argue further pag. 3. from the Assertions of the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in their <hi>humble advice,</hi> as inconsistent: Because (say you) <hi>they acknowledge the divine right to be in the Congregationall Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> That this is <hi>the first and immediate subject of the Divine Right of Presbyterie,</hi> that this <hi>is onely of Divine Right:</hi> and for this you severall times cite their <hi>Humble Advice,</hi> as if some such things were to be found there. But here, Sir, you must give me leave to tell you, that you do most grossely abuse the Assembly with manifest untruths; for there is no such thing to be found in their <hi>Humble Advice,</hi> which I have purposely perused upon this occasion. But say you, <hi>How can these things stand together, that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right is in the Congregationall Presbytery, and yet that there is a Classicall Provinciall and Nationall Presbytery?</hi> Very well, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Principles) for why may not the one be by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right as well as the other? Those of the Congregationall way, or (as you call them) Independents, assert <hi>a Divine Right in a Congregationall Presbytery,</hi> and yet assert withall (in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and discourses frequently) that <hi>Synods are an holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God;</hi> and yet do not think that they contradict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: Your self assert that <hi>the Magistrate is unqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stionably a power
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113583:5"/> of God,</hi> pag. 11. 19. and cite for it <hi>Rom. 13. (The powers that are, are ordained of God</hi>) and by <hi>Magistrate,</hi> I suppose you mean <hi>both Supream and subordinate</hi> (according to the distinction im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. 14.) and hold both the one and the other to be an Ordinance of god; yet will any rationall man hold it a good exception, that <hi>if one be a power of God,</hi> or <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> therfore the other cannot be so? But say you, <hi>THE Divine Right is in the Congregationall Presbyterie, as they acknowledge,</hi> how then can it be any where else? And the Classical, Provincial, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Presbyteries <hi>are but Prudential and Humane, or mixed Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures.</hi> Sir, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cknowledge neither the one nor the other; the most that they acknowledge in the congregational Presbytery is but <hi>A Divine Right,</hi> viz. The same that they assert likewise to be elsewhere (as by their words appears) not <hi>the Divine Right,</hi> as if there were all, and none elsewhere. Much lesse do they acknowledge the other to be but <hi>Prudential or Humane &amp;c.</hi> But do as much assert a Divine Right in the one as in the other.</p>
            <p>You adde, that the Congregational Presbitery <hi>is the first and immediate Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of the Divine Right of Presbitery, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves acknowledge:</hi> Sir, they do not acknowledge any such thing; but rather assert the contrary: Produce any words of theirs to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ense if you can. Though yet I will not deny the some Presbyterians may be of that Judgement.</p>
            <p>You adde, <hi>And now whether do not their own principles control that pretended Right they plead for and set up; a Presbitery of Charity and Prudence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver the Presbytery in the particular Congregation, which they say is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nely of Divine Right.</hi> If their principles and assertions were as you relate them, you might have some cause to speak as you do, and to judge the Assembly to be men of very little Reason; but if they be not so, they may as well beleeve you to be a man of very little <hi>Truth, or Conscience,</hi> who so boldly assert it. You tell us, The Presbytery in the particular Congregation, <hi>They say is onely of Divine Right:</hi> Sir, where do <hi>they say,</hi> that this <hi>onely</hi> is of Divine Right? You cite in the Margin, <hi>See their Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp;c. to the Parl. Manuser. pag.</hi> 4. Sir, I have seen their <hi>Humble Advice,</hi> and I have seen the 4th p. of it; but find not either in that page or in any other, that <hi>this onely is of Divine Right.</hi> That which they assert is this.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113583:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lawfull and agreeable to the Word of God, that the Church be governed by severall sorts of Assemblies; which are Presbyteries and Synods; or Assemblies Congregationall, Classicall, and Synodicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scripture doth hold o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery in a Church,</hi> (and this Presbytery they afterwards assert may be over many Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. <hi>The Scripture doth hold forth, that many particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions may be under one Presbyteriall Government:</hi> and this was asserted on this ground, because <hi>in the Scripture we find it was so.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scripture doth also hold out another sort of Assemblies for the Government of the Church, besides Classicall and Congregationall; which we call Synodicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are their assertions in this point. And now let the Reader judge thereby whether the Assembly do assert, <hi>That the Divines is in the Congregationall Presbytery,</hi> and that <hi>this onely is of Divine Right,</hi> and that others be <hi>but Presbyteries of Charity and Prudence,</hi> but <hi>Prudentiall and Humane or mixed Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures;</hi> or whether they do not as fully assert the Divine Right of the Classicall and Synodicall Assemblies as of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall. And thus I have answered according to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whom you mis-recite.</p>
            <p>Your next Argument, p. 3. &amp;c. <hi>How can that Presbytery whose constitution is so questionable, challenge such a Divine Right?</hi> Sir, we must not grant, that nothing is of Divine Right but what to Mr. <hi>Saltmast</hi> is unquestionable: For I beleeve <hi>Baptisme</hi> to be of Divine Right; yet I beleeve Mr. <hi>Saltmarst</hi> doth not think it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questionable; but rather thinks there ought to be no Baptisme at all.</p>
            <p>Your exceptions against their Presbyters because <hi>ordained</hi> by Bishops, as the Bishops were Presbyters, hath been consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before: And though that Ordination should be null, yet you cannot alledge any thing which your self thinks necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to make a man a <hi>Preacher of the Gospel,</hi> but that they have it.</p>
            <p>You adde, <hi>Their Ruling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> (are ordained) <hi>by a power as questionable, viz. by a Rule of Ordinance of Parliament, &amp;c. not by that very Apostolical Scripture Rule or institution of Jesus Christ. Ans.</hi> The Rule and Institution of their Ruling Elders, they fetch not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113583:6"/> from <hi>Ordinance of Parliament,</hi> but from the Word of God; and their commission from Christ: &amp; assert as much, that <hi>Christ hath instituted a Government and Governors Ecclesiasticall in his Church; And to that purpose the Apostles did immediately receive the keyes from the hands of Jesus Christ, and did use and exercise them in all the Churches of the world upon all occasions; And Christ hath from time to time furnished some in his Church with gifts for Government, and with Commission to exercise the same when called thereunto.</hi> And that <hi>Christ hath furnished some in his Church beside Ministers of the Word with gifts for Government, and with Commission to execute the same when called thereunto; who are to joyn with the Minister in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church; which Officers Reformed Churches commonly call Elders.</hi> And in this point there is no difference between the Presbyterians and those you call Independents. The one do no more fetch their Authority for Ruling Eelders from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament then the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their Congregations</hi> (you say) are <hi>not Congregationall,</hi> (And why not?) but <hi>Parishionall, and of politick constitution.</hi> You mean, that their Congregations are divided, and bounded ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the bounding and division of Parishes, which is of politick constitution. But is it not so in <hi>New-England,</hi> who yet are reputed as the pattern of the Congregational government? Are not the divisions and boundings of their Towns and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes (<hi>Cambridge, New-Plimouth, Boston,</hi> &amp;c.) as much of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Constitution as these of Old-England. Yet are their Congregations divided and bounded accordingly, not some of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> some of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> some of <hi>Boston,</hi> and some of a fourth and fifth place, to make up one Congregation; and other some of all those places to make up a second Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and other some of all those places to make up a third, fourth▪ and fifth Congregation: but the Church Members in such a Town, belong to such a Church; those of another Town to another Church; those of <hi>Cambridge</hi> to the Church of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> those of <hi>New-Plymouth</hi> to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Church of <hi>New-Plymouth,</hi> &amp;c. And those who in any of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e places are not fit to be owned as Church-members, are either to be kept out, or cast out of the Church Communion. And so is it in the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian way. So that neither is here any point of difference. But
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113583:6"/> if (suppose) at <hi>Boston</hi> one be thought fit to be admitted as a Church Member, who if he had lived at <hi>New-Plimouth,</hi> would not by that Church be so esteemed, or one thought fit at <hi>Plimouth,</hi> be not so thought at <hi>Boston;</hi> this makes no altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the rule of their constitution, but onely in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular application of that rule to a present case.</p>
            <p>And thus in the Primitive times; The bounding and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Cities and Countries were as much of Politicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution then as they are now, yet the Churches were bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accordingly: The Christians at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> were of the Church of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> those at <hi>Antioch</hi> of the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> those of <hi>Corinth</hi> of the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> and so the seven Churches of <hi>Asia,</hi> were distinguished according to the seven Cities of <hi>Asia</hi> where they were seated; yet none will question, but that the bounding and parting of those Cities and Townes, <hi>Ephesus, Pergamus, Thiatira, Philadelphia, &amp;c.</hi> were as much of Politicall constitution as our Parishes now.</p>
            <p>As for what you next find fault with, <hi>the constituting the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Presbytery extraordinary by such an Assembly.</hi> If by the <hi>present Presbytery,</hi> you mean, the Government as it is established by the late Ordinances of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and affirme that to be <hi>a Presbytery extraordinary, without Precept or example for such a way in the whole new Testament, &amp;c.</hi> I say onely this to it, that you take a great deal of liberty to speak your pleasure of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; lesse then which might in others be interpreted a breach of their Priviledges. But if by the <hi>present Presbytery,</hi> you mean, what the Assembly advised; they did not advise it as a <hi>Presbytery extraordinary,</hi> nor yet as grounded onely <hi>by way of Analogy on some practises of the Old Testament,</hi> as you intimate; but as the <hi>ordinary way</hi> for the Government of the Church, and as consonant both to the <hi>Precept and practise in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament.</hi> And if what they advise be such, there is no reason why you should except against it because thus <hi>constituted</hi> (you should have said, <hi>advised) by such an Assembly.</hi> For even those who doe not approve of all things that they have advised, (the dissenting Brethren, I mean,) doe not therefore except against it, because by them advised; but doe professe (some of them, with whom I have had some acquaintance, have said it often
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113583:7"/> in my hearing) not onely the <hi>Synods are an holy Ordinance of God,</hi> but particularly of <hi>this Assembly,</hi> that <hi>they beleeve this Assembly so to be, and look upon it as such.</hi> But if your selfe thinke that neither this, nor any other either <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bytery,</hi> may at all be accounted an Ordinance of God, or of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right, because (as your next exception is) they have not Apostolicall and infallible gifts; you must not thinke that either <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Independents</hi> can allow such Principles, as being equally destructive to both. But whether the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly be or be not an Ordinance of God; yet if the thing they advise be an Ordinance of God, it's never the worse for being so advised.</p>
            <p>The next exception against these <hi>Presbyters,</hi> because not <hi>immediately</hi> and <hi>infallibly</hi> gifted as the <hi>Apostles and primitive Elders were;</hi> strikes as much against all Ministery and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in any Church-way whatever, except those of <hi>Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> a late Generation new start up, which no age before these two or three last yeares did ever know; And tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely, by the description your self give of them, (in your <hi>Smoake,</hi> p. 16. and what Principles you here assert, I cannot judge you to be any other then one of them; yea, of the grosser sort of <hi>Seekers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore</hi> (say you) <hi>these present Presbyters</hi> (you should have added, nor any others of what Church-way soever) <hi>cannot challenge the same Power for Church Censures;</hi> (you may adde, or administring any Church Ordinances) <hi>without the same Spirit gifting them, and anoynting them to such a power and Administr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Church:</hi> which you interpret <hi>p.</hi> 5. to be <hi>certain constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and practises,</hi> and not <hi>fallible;</hi> and p. 16. <hi>a gift Divine and Infallible,</hi> and againe, <hi>ibid. They who were Elders or Presbyters in the Churches &amp;c. were gifted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y a Spirit which taught the very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Word which is now written, or Scripture, and so they did constitute, advise, and counsell in the place of this written word, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore there may be no <hi>Presbytery</hi> or Eldership now pleaded as of Divine Right, unlesse such as be as <hi>miraculously,</hi> and <hi>infallibly</hi> gifted as the Apostles were, or as the Papists pretend their Pope to be, yea, as the <hi>Scripture it selfe;</hi> who doth not see that this concludes against all <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments whatsoever, (as well as against those of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113583:7"/> way) for none can governe so infallibly; against all Ministeriall Preaching (as well as ruling) for none can preach so infallibly; against all Baptisme (either of Infants or of grown Christians,) and all Ordinances whatsoever, for none can administer them so infallibly: (which is, I beleeve, that which you aime at:) for <hi>no such thing can be said of any El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dership or Presbytery of men now,</hi> as your selfe acknowledged, p. 16. Yea, against all Magistracy, <hi>especially</hi> intermedling in Church-affaires, as <hi>Baptisme, Presbytery, Church-Order, &amp;c▪</hi> from which you wholly exclude him, as having nothing to do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to injoyn, or punish, in your <hi>Groans for Liberty, p. 17. 19. Consid.</hi> 1. 4. For you there confine his power to bee onely <hi>so farre as concernes any good, or evill either of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or of Nations.</hi> But will not allow it, or the Texts that as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert it, <hi>Rom. 13. 4. 1. Tim. 2. 2. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14. to extend <hi>to a good or evill purely spirituall, and of meere Revelation in the Gospel, as things of Gospell light and Mystery, and notions of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie and Schisme:</hi> and perswade him to be contented <hi>to walk only according to those generall Rules there laid down</hi> (and thus expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) <hi>not DARING to draw bimself to revenge any misbeliefe of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Scripture Mysteries; forcing either side, either for Presbytery, Independency, or Baptisme: Which the Gospell hath no where warranted him in speciall, or in any cleere consequence to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And not onely against their medling with Church affaires, but against their Authority in civill matters also. For the Magistrate cannot (either in Ecclesiastick or Civill affaires) act so Infallibly; and yet say you, <hi>They that challenge a Divine Right to the power they act by</hi> (as surely the Magistrate may, from <hi>Rom. 13. 4. 1 Pet. 2. 13, 14.) must act by a gift as Divine and Infallible as their right and power;</hi> But (say you) <hi>no such thing can be affirmed of any Eldership or Presbytermy</hi> (I adde, nor of any Magistrate or Senate) <hi>of men now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I wonder you should adde that which followes, that they <hi>ought to be content meerly with a mixed and partly pruden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iall power;</hi> especially seeing you direct it against all that plead for a <hi>Divine Right</hi> in any way whatsoever, and yet have not an <hi>infallible Spirit,</hi> which you call a <hi>setting up of a Government for Christs which is not all Christs.</hi> For is not this quite contrary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113583:8"/> to what you do so frequently insist upon, against inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the Civill Power? May not the Magistrate <hi>command the observing of Christs Laws,</hi> and punish the breach of them, (as in the place but now alleadged;) and yet may he now <hi>intermixe</hi> his own <hi>prudence</hi> in <hi>making Lawes?</hi> In your <hi>Grones for liberty, Epist. to Parliament: consid.</hi> 2. you are of opinion that <hi>in the Kingdome of Christ no other Scepter should be lifted up but that golden one of his own, &amp;c. no other Power should rule, no other Scepter, no other Law, &amp;c.</hi> and cite to that purpose in the end of the Booke, <hi>pag.</hi> 36. a large Testimony of Master <hi>Ruterfords, against the Magistrates incroaching on Christs Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> And in your <hi>Smoake</hi> pag. 60. 61. you have a large dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course against <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Scripture Consequences; Once let Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence open a doore, and then will more of man crowd in then the Law of God can keep out.—That which is not direct from Scripture is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct and repugnant.—Nothing is agreable to the will of Christ, but the very will of Christ.—Nothing is agreable to his will but what he wills, and every thing is repugnant to his will but what wills. Christs Rule opposeth any Tradition to the Commandements of God, &amp;c. But if any thing of Prudence is to be let in, then something of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition▪ &amp;c.</hi> and much there to that purpose. I wonder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (if you be now the same man you were then) that you should perswade them to be content with <hi>a mixt and partly pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiall Rule, because of the mixture of their anointing, and gifts,</hi> that is, <hi>because they have not infallible gifts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further; It is but your supposition, (you have no proofe for it) that the <hi>Primitive Elders</hi> were all <hi>infallible;</hi> much lesse that the <hi>Scripture or written word of God,</hi> was but the <hi>Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, forms, and Rules of these Elderships.</hi> It's true that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles in writing and dictating of the Holy Scriptures, and some other Acts that were meerely Apostolick, had an infallible assistance of the Holy Ghost; But we must not thinke that in all their Acts they were thus infallible; nay we know they did erre; <hi>Peter</hi> was in an errour, not only in denying his Master three times (which perhaps you will say, was before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Holy Ghost) but long after, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. (And <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> drawn in to the same dissimulation) and for that error withstood to the face by <hi>Paul. vers.</hi> 11, 12, 13. And <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113583:8"/> though he were in the right, in the case of Circumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Law of <hi>Moses, Acts</hi> 15. yet they doe not rest in his Apostolick Spirit, but send to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to have the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie adjudged; And as for other Elders who were not Apostles, we have no intimation at all of their infallibility, no more then we have of the infallibility of your self, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters now: Yea, we are sure they did erre, and (some of them) fall away; for not onely <hi>Judas</hi> proved a Traiterous Apostle; but <hi>Demas</hi> afterward forsook <hi>Paul</hi> to imbrace the present world: And <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Deacon, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. (though or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by laying on the Apostles hands, which you conceive to conferre an infallible gift of the holy Ghost.) Is, at least supposed to be, the Author of the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> which God hates, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. And others that pretended to the Apostles <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 2. came under tryall and were found lyers.</p>
            <p>Yea, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> so farre differed, not onely in point of Judgement, (in which they could not both judge aright) but in matter of affection too, that upon a hot contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a third person <hi>John Mark,</hi> for a former miscarriage (who it seems was not infallible) that they parted the one from the other in dislike, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 39. in which carriage they could not both be in the right: which parting, you know (I beleeve) that the dissenting Brethren make their ground of <hi>Non-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> of Churches, which is the highest censure they judge any Church for the greatest errour to be capable of; and therefore if these Apostles did the one Non-Communicate the other, certainly the one or the other was in an errour. And <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20. tells the <hi>Elders of Ephesus,</hi> that even <hi>of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves should men arise speaking perverse things;</hi> So that these El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> though <hi>Primitive Elders</hi> were not <hi>infallible.</hi> Yea the <hi>Angells</hi> of the seven Churches, <hi>Rev. 2. &amp;</hi> 3. had their errors; The Angel of the Church of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> (the Eldership there) <hi>had left their first love, Rev.</hi> 2. 4. and are threatned with remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall of the Candle-stick unlesse they repent: And the like threatned to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving these that held the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam:</hi> And the Angel of the Church of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea</hi> threatned to be spued out for being neither hot nor cold;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113583:9"/> and so of the rest. By all which appeares, that neither the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders nor the Elderships were then infallible.</p>
            <p>And therefore, to tell us that <hi>the word of the Gospell</hi> was <hi>part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the gifts of those Elderships,</hi> and that those Elderships <hi>did constitute, advise, and counsell in the place of the written Word;</hi> and that <hi>for any to assume such a power as they did, is to sit down in the Throne of Scripture or very word of God,</hi> and that a power of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right,</hi> (which you say the Magistrate hath undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>without a sure and infallible Spirit for Church-censures, or the execution of such a power, is to joyn such with the infallible word or Scripture, and to controll the pure word of Truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y an Interpretation lesse then Truth;</hi> is little lesse then blasphemy: making the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions, Advice and Councells</hi> of the Elders and Elderships then, (for some of which Christ threatens to spue them out of his mouth, to remove the Candlestick, &amp;c. to be equall with the Scripture and written word of God, and to have a Power to controll the pure word of Truth. For if they had not such infallibility and such a Power then, they who assume the same power which they did, do not assume this now.</p>
            <p>As for what you adde of Ordination, that the present Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters are not ordained by <hi>christ himselfe,</hi> by the <hi>Apostles,</hi> or such as immediately <hi>received their power from the Apostles;</hi> is but to delude the world, whom you would have to think that you onely oppose <hi>the present Presbytery,</hi> as you call it, but do indeed oppose <hi>all Presbytery,</hi> (and indeed, all Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ever was, in any of the ages of the Church since the Apostles times) for <hi>none</hi> are so ordained; And whereas you add, nor <hi>by a power in the Church or Congregation, preceding such a power and accompanying such a power;</hi> as if you would approve of such an Ordination as in some Churches of the Congregationall way, is performed by the People; is but further to delude: For I ask you seriously, whether you think such Presbyters rightly ordained, and to be of Divine Right? If so, then by your grounds, they must have <hi>a Divine and infallible Gift,</hi> If not rightly ordained, then do you as much oppose those of the <hi>Congregationall way,</hi> yea, and all of <hi>whatever way,</hi> as you doe those for the <hi>present Presbytery:</hi> For the things which you say are requisite to Presbyters by Divine Right, are not (you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113583:9"/> to be said of <hi>any Eldership or Presbytery of men now.</hi> Yea and though you here seem to approve of such an Ordination, and such a power in the Church; yet you know it is one of your exceptions against Independency (in your <hi>Smoak, pag. 10.) That there is not such a power radically or fundamentally in the Church to make Pastors and Elders, because there is first no such practise in the word, but rather an Apostolicall or Ministeriall Power, which made or gathered Churches first, not Churches them:</hi> And <hi>that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Ordination, was by the Apostles, and a power established in the Presbytery, not in the Church, as meer Beleevers.</hi> So that still your dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is to oppose all things, and establish nothing.</p>
            <p>Your last Engine of opposing a Divine Right in Presbytery, is, <hi>a fear least all the magistracy and State power in the Kingdom and the Parliament of England may fall under their cognizance, if they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume a spirit of judging and discerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and how dangerous this would be to the State, Histories will shew.</hi> But this is but the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of those <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4. against the building of Jerusalem and the house of God in it, because it was <hi>a rebellious citie, hurtfull to Kings and Provinces,</hi> and of those against Christ, <hi>Joh. 19. He that maketh himself a King speaketh against Caesar,</hi> though (he had told them before that <hi>His Kingdom was not of this world.)</hi> But you who are else where so much against <hi>carnall reason, consulting with flesh and blood, humane prudence</hi> and the <hi>wisdome of the flesh;</hi> might have spared such an Argument. If (in your <hi>Groans</hi>) you do not think it fair for them to charge <hi>Schisme</hi> on you, you should not here insinuate <hi>Sedition</hi> in them: At least, unlesse your Histories which you speak of, could have shewed you that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Presbiterians in <hi>France,</hi> though under a Popish King, or those in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> in <hi>Geneva,</hi> or in some other places had thus imbrolyed States and Countries.</p>
            <p>Again, you are to consider that the question at present in hand, is not about the power of a Nationall Assembly, but the Congregationall Presbyterie; at least if that be true which you affirm so confidently (p. 3. and elsewere) that <hi>they say, this is onely a Divine Right.</hi> For if they hold this onely to be of Divine Right, then the Divine Right which they plead for must beonely the Divine Right of the Congregationall, not the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall, Presbyterie. But, say you, <hi>shall not this Nationall Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113583:10"/> take cognizance of States, if sinning, Ecclesiastically as well as others.</hi> Sir, If by <hi>taking cognizanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> you mean admonishing them of their duty, and shewing the danger of Gods displeasure if they fail of it; I grant that they may thus take notice of it: The Prophets did so of old in the Kingdom of Israel, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Minister called to preach to one or both Houses of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, may and ought so to do; for else were it a mocking of God and of his Ordinances, to require his servants to speak to them in his Name, if they may not deliver his message: If by <hi>taking Cognizance,</hi> you mean, <hi>censuring o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> excommunicating;</hi> you know 1. that the subject of the Petition, and the Divine Right there pleaded, is not about <hi>Excommunication</hi> at all, much lesse the <hi>Excommunication of a State,</hi> but about <hi>keeping scandalous and ignorant persons</hi> from the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> now States nad Kingdoms, do not receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, but persons; and consequently States and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms are not debarred from it, but persons; and thus if a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that is member of such a State be unfit to be admitted, he may and ought to be kept away.</p>
            <p>2. If the question had been about Excommunication (which is also of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and so asserted by these Petitioners, though not in that Petition, there being no occasion to speak of it there) yet you know that the Reformed Churches do not Excommunicate Kingdoms, or Parliaments, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; For if they should do so, they should excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate the Innocent together with the Nocent, for a minor part may be wholly innocent of what by a major part is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled: as for instance, the twelve Judges in the Chequer cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the case of Shipmoney, are reputed to have given Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it, because the major part was for it; yet had it been injustice for that Court to have censured all (either Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally or civilly) when some of them (though not a major part) gave judgement against it; nor did the Parliament in that case censure them all, but those onely who were offenders. Much lesse can it be imagined that a Parliament or Kingdom can be the subject of Excommunication: because they cannot be all presumed nocent; nor is the Parliament, as a Parliament, or a Magistrate as a Magistrate, a Church Member, no more then a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113583:10"/> Magistrate as a Magistrate is a Church Officer, and therefore cannot as such be excommunicated. But if those persons that be Members of Parliament, be, in their personal capacity, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of such crimes as may deserve excommunication, I know not that Christ hath more exempted them from it, then he hath exempted other persons. 3. And I adde withall, that this is not a Tenet of the Presbyterians onely, but of us all, whether Presbyterian, or Congregationall; For if a Member of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be a Member of an Independent or Congregationall Church (as it is called) no question but they have the same power over him, that they have over the rest of the Members. (Nay further, though the Presbyterians do not excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Societies, but onely persons, yet those of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall way do <hi>Non-communicate</hi> not onely persons, who are their own Members, but whole Societies and Churches.) And therefore that fear of <hi>excommunicating</hi> Parliaments and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, which you speak of, is but a bugbear.</p>
            <p>You conclude at last, that <hi>when the Parliament is perswaded of no Divine Right, the Assembly of a Divine Right, and the Dissenting Brethren of another Divine Right,</hi> (you should have added, The An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>baptists of a third Divine Right, the Seekers of a fourth, the Papists of a fifth, the Jews of a sixth, the Turks of a seventh, &amp;c.) <hi>the way is to let the Parliament have their liberty of Conscience to settle no Divine Right</hi> (nor is it desired; they are desired onely to settle the thing, not to settle the Divine Right of it) <hi>and the Assembly to use their Liberty in a Divine Right,</hi> (but this is that will not be granted, but they are required to act thus, <hi>and not otherwise,</hi> which Independents can no more approve of in their Consciences then Presbyterians) <hi>and the other Brethren as peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to enjoy their other Divine Right:</hi> (you should have added, and so for all the rest, every one to enjoy their own supposed Divine Right.) But Sir, what if it be the Parliaments Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they ought not to suffer all these to enjoy and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise their supposed Divine Rights, but think themselves bound to su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>presse them, or some of them; must the Parliament <hi>in this Straight</hi> (as you speak) <hi>enjoy their Liberty of Conscien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> to suppresse them? If not, tell us why all others must be suffered to practise according to their own Consciences, though erron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113583:11"/> and yet the Parliament not to practise thus if it be their Conscience?</p>
            <p>And thus much for your <hi>Reasons,</hi> and the Principles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from them.</p>
            <p>I Come next to examine your <hi>Inferences</hi> on <hi>the last Petition of the Assembly, for Divine Right in their present Presbytery:</hi> Sir, they did not <hi>Petition</hi> for a Divine Right; that which they petitioned is this, and only this, <hi>that the severall Elderships may be sufficiently enabled to keep back all such, as are notoriously seandalous from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper:</hi> And in this we all agree; for this is a Tenent common to <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and Independents, as they are called, yea more insisted upon by the latter, <hi>That this power of keeping from the Lords Table all Ignorant, and scandalous persons doth of Divine Right, belong to the Eldership</hi> and this (say those of the Congregationall way) <hi>without appeale,</hi> much lesse can they allow of the Commissioners there provided: but do in their Consciences fully beleeve them to be unlawfull, and contrary to the word of God. And the Divine Right asserted in the Petition, (not petitioned for) is no more but what both parties do agree in.</p>
            <p>If you object, that Independents have been great Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of these Commissioners, and pleaders for them; &amp;c. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse some of them, many of them, have so; (But I thank God, I am not to answer for that.) This I know, that they cannot in their Congregations admit of such Commissioners to be Judges, to determine who shall, and who shall not, come to their Sacraments; But how they can consent to the setting up of what themselves judge unlawfull, I know not; nor will I undertake to give an account, let them answer for themselves; perhaps it is according to their Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science so to do. But I proceed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Preface</hi> of the Petition you omit, and say nothing to; wherein the Assembly shew, <q>
                  <hi>That they cannot but with joy remember the marveilous goodnesse of God, in calling, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Parliament, in the time of this Nations greatest trouble and danger, and in making it singularly usefull towards the saving of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113583:11"/> these three Nations, from the bondage of Tyranny and Idolatry, by taking off many yokes and burdens, both in matters of Religion and of Civill Government; by laying the foundations and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of a positive Reformation; and by ingaging this Kingdome in that solemne and sacred League and Covenant, which with our hands lifted up to the most High God we have sworn.</hi>
               </q> And adde further, <q>That <hi>as they esteem themselves, alwayes bound to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge these, and many other blessings, which the God of Heaven hath made this Honourable Parliament, his Instruments to convey unto these poore Kingdomes, with all aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctionate thankfullnesse to God, and to the Honourable Houses, so they professe themselves the more obliged thereby, to shew all active readinesse to promote all the Commands of Parliament, tending to Reformation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that nothing but Conscience of their duty to God, to the Parliament themselves, and the soules of the rest of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the People of the Lord, could excuse in them any seeming back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, to act according to the Votes, and Ordinances of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament leading thereunto.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The next <hi>Part</hi> of the Petition, and that which you take notice of, contains the particulars wherein they desire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse, as thinking themselves aggrieved in them, and being unsatisfied in their Consciences about them. <hi>viz.</hi> That the enumeration of Scandalls is yet defective; and the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners are Officers of which they cannot approve. <q>
                  <hi>Yet are we</hi> (say they) <hi>to our grief constrained at this time, in all Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Faithfulnesse, to represent to the Honourable Houses, That there is still a great defect in the enumeration of scandalous sins; very many scandalous sins ordinarily committed in all places, and formerly presented by your Petitioners, being still omitted.</hi>
               </q> Which, it's like, they added, because of that aspersion cast upon them abroad, as if they had onely desired an indefinite power of keeping away scandalous persons, and had never given in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in any particulars; or at least, that they had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stanced in any other then those enumerated in the severall Ordinances of Parliament, and that if they would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stanced in any other they should have been inserted. The next particular you repeat, <q>
                  <hi>And that the Provision of Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners to judge the scandals not enumerated, appeares to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113583:12"/> to be so contrary to that way of Government, which Christ hath appointed in his Church.</hi>
               </q> And then infer from it, <hi>That the Assembly do suppose the Parliament, and Commissioners to be far below the Ministers and Eldership, in spirituall gifts and discerning;</hi> and that this is, <hi>to set up the old aistinction of Laity and Clergy;</hi> but <hi>seeing the gifts</hi> (of the Ministers and Magistrates) <hi>are not so distinct;</hi> you ask <hi>why the Offices should be so distinct.</hi> Sir, the Assembly do suppose, and more then suppose (and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the Assembly too) that Ministers and Elderships may do something, which neither the Commissioners nor Parliament may do. That the Parliament and Commissioners may not administer the Word and Sacraments, is granted by all, (what ever become of Church-Censures;) and it is as much grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Ministers may: It's granted by all (except See<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers) that Ministers may ordain Ministers, but I never heard t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at a Parliament may ordain Ministers: And yet this hath not been accounted hitherto <hi>a setting the Minister upon a higher forme then the Magistrate,</hi> as you now charge it: And why should it be thought more unreasonable, to say the same of Church-Censures? For those who do acknowledge Church-Censures at all, acknowledge that they are to be inflicted by Church Officers, yet do not deny the Authority of the Parliament or Civill Magistrate; to whom the Sword is committed, but not the Keys. But, what ever become of Church-Censures, yet the distinction will remain still (though not between Clergy and Laity, as you speak, yet) between Church-Officers, and other Church Members, and between Ministers and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates. For else you must say, that a Magistrate by being a Magistrate is made a Minister, and a Minister by being a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister is made a Magistrate; and you can no more say the one then the other. And if alike question to that of yours, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a distinction of Offices without a distinction of Gifts, (as you suppose) should be put in another case; seeing the Gifts of a Justice of Peace, or a Judge, are not so distinct from the Gifts of other men, why should there be a distinction of Office? or, seeing the gifts of Parliament men are not so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct from the gifts of other men, why should their Office be distinct? It would easily be answered, that it is not Gifts, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113583:12"/> Commission, and a lawfull Calling, that makes a Justice, a Judge, a Parliament man; And in like manner, not Gifts, but Commission from Christ, and a lawfull Call that makes a Minister.</p>
            <p>You proceed next to their next words, <q>
                  <hi>In that it giveth a Power to judge of the fitnesse of persons to come to the Sacraments, unto such persons as our Lord Christ hath not given that power unto.</hi>
               </q> Against which you object, <hi>That the Magistrate who is unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably the power of God, may more lawfully judge of sins, and Gospel Rules, then they who are a questionable Ministry and Eldership.</hi> But Sir. You cannot affirme this or that Magistrate to be a Power of God, more then this or that Minister: and Ministers (indefinitely) are as much undoubtedly an ordinance of God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Magistrates. 2. Though the Magistrate be unquestionably <hi>a Power of God, and a Judge of good and evill,</hi> yet he is not unquesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably a <hi>Judge of sins, and Gospel Rules;</hi> for your self, question it, yea deny it, in the places even now alledged out of your <hi>Groans for Liberty, p.</hi> 17, 18, 19. where you confine the Good and evil of which he is Judge, onely to what is good or evill <hi>of the Law of Nature or Nations,</hi> and exclude him from medling with <hi>a good or evill purely spirituall, and of meer revelation in the Gospel,</hi> and amongst these you reckon <hi>things of Gospel Light and Mystery; and Notions of Heresie and Schisme; particulars of Truth and Heresie; the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wayes of practises in things of outward cognizance and Order, as Baptisme, Church Order, &amp;c. Gospel Mysteries, such as Presbytery, Independency, or Baptisme,</hi> (you might as well have added, <hi>the Lord Supper;) the misbeliefe of such particular Scripture Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> and in generall <hi>things of spirituall cognizance:</hi> in these things you would not have him <hi>DARE</hi> to interpose his power, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>which the Gospel hath no where warranted him in speciall, or in any cleare consequence to do;</hi> and such a <hi>latitude of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the generall Rules in the Gospel concerning Magistracy, (Rom. 13. 4. 1. Tim. 2. 2. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14.) as to extend it to things of this nature, you cannot approve of. And in the <hi>Epist:</hi> you would have <hi>no Scepter lifted up in Christs Kingdome, but that golden one of his own.</hi> And therefore the Magistrate, according to your Principles is not in these things an <hi>unquestionable power of God.</hi> Nay further; if your other Principle be good (<hi>That
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113583:13"/> they who challenge a Divine Right to the power they act by, must act by a gift as Divine and infallible as their right and power,</hi>) he will not be an <hi>unquestionable power of God</hi> in any thing; For if in any thing he be <hi>unquestionably a power of God,</hi> or ordained by God, he must therein act by a gift <hi>unquestionably Divine and infallible:</hi> which seeing he cannot do, he must, by your Principles, disclaime any <hi>Divine Right</hi> at all to the power he acts by, either in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall or Civill affaires, and must no longer pretend to be a <hi>power of God,</hi> or <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> till he can attain at such <hi>infallible Gifts.</hi> And now how good a friend you are to the Magistrate, when you do (in termes) deny his power in all things of <hi>Spirituall cognizance,</hi> and (by consequence) in things of a <hi>Civill cognizance</hi> too; is easie to see. But, Sir, as I doubt not to allow the Magistrate a power, (which you would not have him <hi>DARE</hi> to take,) notwithstanding that you think it <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionable;</hi> so neither do I doubt, but that Ministers and Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships may in these dayes be the <hi>Ministry and Eldership of Jesus Christ,</hi> though it be to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Questionable.</hi> For if every thing must be presently <hi>Disclaimed,</hi> as soone as Mr. <hi>Saltmarsh</hi> begins to think it <hi>Questionable,</hi> we shall soon bring Religion to a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compasse.</p>
            <p>The next words of the Petition <q>(<hi>And also layeth upon us a necessitie of admitting some scandalous person to the Sacrament even after conviction before the Eldership;</hi>)</q> you say nothing to; but proceed to repeat those that follow, <q>
                  <hi>And to be so differing from all example of the best reformed Churches, and such a reall hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the bringing the Churches of God in the three kingdoms to the neerest conjunction and Ʋniformity, and in all these re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects so disagreeable to our Covenant, that we dare not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise according to that provision.</hi>
               </q> And from hence you infer, <hi>That if all do not beleeve as one beleeves, it is pretended, that all are in breach of Covenant:</hi> No Sir, you cannot infer so much; but this you may infer, <hi>That those who do not endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms to the nearest Conjunction and Ʋniformity,</hi> are in a bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch of Covenant; (and this cannot be denyed, for it is the very Letter of the Covenant) and therfore they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this (as they affirm) to be a <hi>reall kinderance</hi> to that which they had covenanted to endeavour, conceived them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113583:13"/> bound to petition the removall of it. And you who (in your <hi>Smoke, &amp;c. p.</hi> 24, 25, 26. In your <hi>Argument from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for Liberty of Conscience,</hi>) allow the Magistrate to be the Interpreter of the Covenant, in things <hi>Morall, Civill, or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular cognizance</hi> only, and do exclude his interpretation in <hi>Gospell mysteries,</hi> in things <hi>immediately Divine and spirituall;</hi> and hold that <hi>in the things of God,</hi> in <hi>all things of spirituall cognizan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, as every Scripture Truth, or Truth in the word is,</hi> there is no other Judge and Interpreter to each mans Conscience, but <hi>the Lord Jesus, and the Spirit of Jesus Christ;</hi> and that <hi>each man standing ingaged in his own particular, and in his own proper Conscience by a Covenant recommended and imposed, each is bound to bring forth the Evidences of their Consciences in particular, concerning this to which they are covenanted;</hi> and every one <hi>stands bound by their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Consciences to reveale to the State, what their Consciences inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret, &amp;c.</hi> I say, you who hold thus, cannot blame the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly for revealing to the Parliament, that <hi>this provision of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, &amp;c. appeares to their Consciences, to be—a reall hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the bringing of the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the nearest conjunctions and uniformity.</hi> Especially when they say withall, not only that thinke it in their Conscience thus to be, but also that they dare not in Conscience hold their peace; as appeares in the following words, <q>
                  <hi>And we do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently foresee, that such Commissioners will not onely be offensive to the Reformed Churches abroad, but a discouragement to those a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst our selves, who either are or shall be chosen Elders, and a stumbling block to very many of our best, and most conscientious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who have long waited for Reformation, and are in danger to be cast upon the snare of separation, and no way left to reduce them, or others who are already fallen into it: Insomuch as we cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to professe our feares of Gods sad displeasure if this should be continued; and the just imputation of sinne unto us, if we who have been held worthy by the Honourable Houses, to be called to give them advise in matters of Religion, should altogether hold our peace at this time.</hi>
               </q> But why the word <hi>Ʋniformity</hi> should so much displease, as it seemes it doth, I cannot tell; There is a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in the <hi>Congregationall way</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Presbyteriall way</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and to what you say, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113583:14"/> the Uniformity in the Covenant is <hi>the Ʋniformity with the word, not with one another;</hi> That it is a Uniformity <hi>with the word</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true; but why not <hi>with one another?</hi> Surely if we must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring all to a Uniformisy with the word, the other is included; for if all be Uniforme to the word, and the word uniforme to it selfe, there will be a Uniformity one with another. But the thing you plead for, is not that every one should be uniforme to the word, but that every one should follow their own way; telling us, that <hi>Ʋnity in the Spirit makes up Ʋniformity in the Letter,</hi> that <hi>Communion in Ʋnity is a glorious supplement to the rent of Ʋniformity, p.</hi> 12. 19 and thereupon like not the pressing of the Covenant for Uniformity: As if when you had taken the Covenant, you had not covenanted to <hi>endeavour a Ʋniformity,</hi> but to endeavour <hi>something instead of Ʋniformity,</hi> as a <hi>glorious supplement</hi> for the want of it; and this <hi>something,</hi> had been, <hi>a liberty for every one to practise what they thought good:</hi> A principle which the <hi>Congregationall Churches</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> disavow, as well as the <hi>Presbyterian Churches</hi> in <hi>France, Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next words you touch at, are those int he Petitory part of the Petition, which runs thus, <q>
                  <hi>Wherefore your Petitioners in discharge of their fidelity to God, to his Church, and to your Honours, humbly pray, that the severall Elderships may be sufficiently enabled to keep back All such as are notoriously scandalous from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </q> Hence you inferre, <hi>that they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to raise up the interest of the Eldership, and Presbytery, into a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct, sole, and independent body and power.</hi> No Sir, not <hi>a sole and Independent Power;</hi> for that is the great question between them and the dissenting Brethren, whether the power of particular Elderships be Independent: But they plead for a <hi>sufficiency of Power,</hi> to keep from the Sacrament all scandalous persons; which is no more then (yea not so much as) the Protestant Churches in <hi>France</hi> do injoy under a Popish King; nor more then Christian Churches practised both under Christian, and Heathen Emperours: Nor more then every gathered Congregation amongst us at this day, do take to themselves without asking leave, admitting to, and keeping from their Congregations whom they think good; you should not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113583:14"/> under pretence of opposing the Assemblies Petition, cast dirt upon your friends, and all the godly party; who have many of them left the Churches of England, and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, meerly upon this ground, of <hi>mixt Communi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> Yea, Sir, I wonder with what Conscience you can oppose this as an unreasonable demand; when your selfe do frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly speak so broadly against the Magistrates power, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle, or ingage his Sword in <hi>matters of Religion,</hi> things of <hi>Worship,</hi> particulars of <hi>Scripture Truth, Baptisme, Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp;c.</hi> which for my part, I dare not do, because I doubt not of the Magistrates power to interpose his Civill Authority: Nor do they whom you here tax for craving too much; who in expresse terms ascribe it to him: And those whom you would perhaps be thought to plead for (though indeed you plead against them) the dissenting Brethren, who in their <hi>Apologeticall Narration, p.</hi> 19. professe themselves <hi>to give to the Civill Magistrate, as much, and (as they think) more, then the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Presbyteriall Government will suffer them to yield.</hi> And therefore neither one nor other can approve of the Anti-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistraticall Tenets, in denying the Magistrate not onely a power of Ecclesiasticall, but of Civill a Censures too, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Gospel Truths,</hi> and of <hi>Spirituall cognizance:</hi> though both the one, and the other, beleeve that to be due to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derships, which is here asked; and your selfe (according to your Principles) must say, the Magistrate hath nothing to do with it.</p>
            <p>You inferre further; that <hi>Petitioning a power from the State to compleat, and make up an Eldership, doth, either imply an Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power in the State (for the State cannot give what it selfe hath not) or else 'tis a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> contradiction to pray for that from the State which it cannot give.</hi> But your inference will not hold: They ask not of the State an <hi>Ecclesiasticall power,</hi> but a <hi>Liberty to exercise</hi> hat Power, which (they say here) they receive from other hands, by Divine Right, and the appointment of Jesus Christ; and this is no more then the State may give, though yet they have not that themselves: the State may, and doth authorize and enable (by their Civill Authority) a Minister to preach the word, and administer the Sacraments in their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113583:15"/> but doth not give him that Ecclesiasticall Power where by he is a Minister, but only a Liberty to exercise that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which he received in his Ordination. When your selfe, by the <hi>Committee for plundered Ministers,</hi> was put into the <hi>Sequestra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Brasted;</hi> you were by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enabled and authorized to Officiate there, and all required to permit you so to do; yet this was not an Ecclesiasticall but a Civill power which they exercised, in giving you leave, to exercise an Ecclesiasticall Power (of administring the word and Sacraments,) which Ecclesiasticall Power though they might give you leave to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise, (supposing you then to be a Minister, for you had not then disclaimed your Ordination) yet had not power to exercise it themselves. And so when you afterwards obtained an Order from the <hi>Committee of Examinations,</hi> to keep a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture at a place neare adjoyning. A King by his <hi>Politicall</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may authorize and enable a Master, a Father, a Husband to exercise their respective <hi>Domesticall</hi> duties, which himselfe (though he may give them leave to do it) may not do. And so he may as a Magistrate give leave to another, to exercise his Ministeriall power; though yet he can neither make him a Minister, nor exercise that power himself. And if the State with us should give leave, and authorize Churches of the Congregationall way to exercise their own way, according to their own judgements, they would not refuse to accept of it; nor yet think that they did thereby make the State power to be Ecclesiasticall.</p>
            <p>From their next words <q>(<hi>Of which we must (as formerly we have done) say expressely, It belongs unto them by Divine Right, and by the will and appointment of Jesus Christ. Which with help of superio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Assemblies in cases of Appeale, or in Mal-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations therein, will prevent (through the blessing of God) all the feared inconveniences,</hi>
               </q> You inferre, <hi>That the Presbytery and Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; of a Congregation i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Divine Right.</hi> Their word was <hi>Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships;</hi> and no question but the Assembly holds Elderships to be of Divine Right, and so do you too, if you be of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall way.</p>
            <p>But you inferre further, That this <hi>Divine Right is perfected and compleated, by that which is not of as pure Divine Right as it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113583:15"/> viz. Superior Assemblies.</hi> What you mean by <hi>perfected and compleated,</hi> I cannot tell; but that they may <hi>receive help</hi> from Superiour Assemblies, (which is all the Petition asserts) is without Controversie in the Judgement, both of Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Independents: who both agree, that <hi>Synods are an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God;</hi> and that they may afford much help to infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Presbyteries or Elderships. See Mr. <hi>Cottons Keys of the Kingdome of Heaven, chap. 6. per totum:</hi> and the Epistle to it, by Mr. <hi>Th: Goodwin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Nye,</hi> Witnesse also the <hi>Apologet, Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat: p. 21. That it is a most abhorrid Maxime, that any Religion hath ever made profession of, and therefore of all other the most contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and dishonourable unto that of Christianity, that a single and particular society of men, professing the name of Christ, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be endowed with a power from Christ to judge them that are of the same body and Society with themselves, should further ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate unto themselves an exemption from giving Account, or being Censurable by any other, either Christian Magistrate above them, or neighbour Churches about them.</hi> And whosoever shall peruse the severall Uses of <hi>Synods</hi> mentioned by Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in his <hi>Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> and published by two of those Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Apologists; cannot doubt, but that in their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Synods may be very helpfull to Elderships: And when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth by Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> and by the Dissenting Brethren, Synods are owned and asserted to be <hi>an Ordinance of God,</hi> I know no reason why you should not judge them of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pure Divine Right</hi> as the other. For though they do not beleeve, that <hi>a Synod may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate,</hi> yet they never make question, but that a <hi>Synod is an holy Ordinance of God.</hi> Nor do I well understand your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in those words; that the Synod <hi>is not of as pure Divine Right</hi> as the Eldership: You cannot assert it as <hi>your own Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for, I beleeve, you do not hold either of them to be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right: Nor can you mean it of the <hi>Assemblies Judgement,</hi> for they affirm, that both are of Divine Right. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what will become of of this Inference I cannot tell.</p>
            <p>You proceed to repeat their next words, <q>
                  <hi>And the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, to whom we professe the Church to be accountable for their proceedings in all their Elderships, and Church Assemblies, and punishable by him with Civill Censures for their miscarriages, may
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113583:16"/> be so abundantly satisfied of the righteousnesse and equity thereof; as we still hope God will inspire the Honourable Houses with such wisdome and zeal, as by their Authority to strengthen the hands of his Officers in their duties herein, and even to command them to act zealously and faithfully therein. And your Petitioners, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Hence you inferre, <hi>That the Magistrate is neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r over the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, for Commissioners are contrary to the word, nor under the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, for the Presbytery is accountable to him: and where to place him by this Petition you cannot tell.</hi> But surely Sir, you are not so ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in this matter, as you would seeme to make your selfe. You know that both the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall</hi> Principles deny the Magistrate to be a <hi>Church Offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> or to have Power to administer the <hi>Word,</hi> or <hi>Sacraments,</hi> or <hi>Church-Censures,</hi> and for this reason cannot approve of the Commissioners; But do not deny him, as a <hi>Civill Officer,</hi> a power to exercise <hi>Civill Censures,</hi> upon <hi>Ecclesiasticall Persons</hi> as well as others, even for their miscarriages in their <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Imployments:</hi> And this is that the Petition asserts. Your self, it's true, deny both, and allow the Magistrate <hi>in Gospell Truths, and things of Spirituall Cognizance,</hi> no power at all, either of Ecclesiasticall or Civill Censure: but those you oppose, though they cannot grant to the Magistrate the exercise of the <hi>Keys,</hi> yet they never denyed him the power of the <hi>Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you urge again, <hi>p.</hi> 21 (for you had said it at least five or six times in substance before) that they are but <hi>pretended Officers, Ministers Elders,</hi> that it is not <hi>a Church in Gospel-Order,</hi> that they <hi>must prove the truth both of their very Church, Ministry, and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dership,</hi> that <hi>the Magistrate may more lawfully rule then any other pretended Officer, Minister, or Elder,</hi> that <hi>they cannot exclude the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Power from governing with them according to the unsound Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of their Churches, &amp;c.</hi> It seems then, that if their Churches were▪ soundly constituted, you allow an excluding of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Power. 2. I aske whether you think, that the Magistrates exercising Church Censures, do make the Church to be of a more sound Constitution? and, if so, I aske by what Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture you prove, that this is necessary to their sound Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3. Your opinion is (if you remember what you have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113583:16"/> said formerly) that, be the Constitution sound or unsound' the Magistrate is not to meddle at all with matters of <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cognizance,</hi> with <hi>particulars of Truth and Heresie,</hi> with <hi>Baptisme, Church Order, &amp;c.</hi> as before is shewed. 4. They do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that <hi>the Magistrate may rule amonst them,</hi> they do not <hi>exclude the Civill power from governing,</hi> nay, they positively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it in this Petition; onely they say, he should do it by <hi>Civill Censures,</hi> not by <hi>Church Censures;</hi> but your selfe (as you may remember) deny both the one and the other. 5. If you had said, that because the Constitution of the Church is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sound, therefore there should be no administring of the word, the Sacraments or Church-Censures at all, you had said some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and spoken like your selfe; but how doth it appeare that the Magistrate must do it? That the Magis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rate may punish with civill Censures is very true; but that he may do be their Constitution sound or unsound; but how comes it to passe that he hath thereby a power of <hi>Church Censure</hi> more then he had before? Hath Christ hath said that the Keys shall be used in a sound Church by the Ministers and Elderships, but in an unsound Church by the Magistrate? that the word or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments shall be administred in a sound Church by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, in an unsound Church by the Magistrate? That in a sound Church the Church Officers shall excommunicate, but in an unsound Church the Magistrate shall do it? If he have said it, pray tell us the place, that we may know where, he hath said it. But doubtlesse the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> doth not proceed upon this Principle, That because the Churches of <hi>England</hi> are no true Churches, and the Ministry of <hi>England</hi> no true Ministry, therefore they may not be trusted with Church Censures: And therefore if you have no other ground to goe upon, you do not plead their cause, nor will they own that Principle under what disguise soever. And for the thing it selfe, whether they be true Churches or no; you must bring a better Argument to overthrow them, then what at present you insist upon▪ (<hi>That they have not an infallible Spirit</hi>) unlesse you mean at once to deny all Churches, Ministers, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the either are, or have been in the world since the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles time. And if that be your meaning, you may do well
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113583:17"/> to speak it out, that the world may know what you are.</p>
            <p>What you insinuate in your Epistle, As if the Assembly had intrenched upon the Priviledges of the Parliament, or at least gone beyond their owne bounds; I have nothing to say to. I am no Judge of the Assemblies Bounds, or the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Priviledges: neither do I undertake to defend it against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but against Mr. <hi>Saltmarsh;</hi> and that I think is sufficiently done. But what you complaine of afterwards, that <hi>since Truth hath had its lot in the world to live upon Voyces in Assemblies, and Synods, where that is only Truth which is voted so; and not in its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn glory and evidence, where that is only Truth that is so; the Mystery of Iniquity hath been more advanced then the Mystery of Godlinesse;</hi> is no complaint of the Assemblies Exorbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cancy, but of the being of Assemblies: and (by consequence) against the being of Senates or civill Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icatures: For I shall not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to see the same pen say as much of the Parliament, (for there will be the same reason for both) especially if they shall do that which he would not have them <hi>DARE</hi> to do, that is, meddle with <hi>Gospel Truths, particulars of Truth and Heresie, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, Church-Order, &amp;c.</hi> or such other things as he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted not only from their <hi>Ecclesiasticall,</hi> but from their <hi>Civill Censure</hi> too: For the Parliaments voting a thing to be Truth, will no more make it a truth, if it be not so in it self, then the Assemblies voting it so to be. And perhaps he may in time, (for he doth not reveale all his light at once) say as much of <hi>Justice,</hi> as he doth now of <hi>Truth:</hi> that <hi>since</hi> Justice <hi>hath had its Lot in the world to live upon Voyces in Assemblies and</hi> Senates, <hi>where that is onely</hi> Equity <hi>which is voted so; and not in its own glory and evidence, wbere that is onely</hi> Equity <hi>which is so: the Mystery of</hi> Iniquity <hi>hath been advanced, &amp;c.</hi> For, that latent Principle (<hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the major part of men are naught</hi>) will serve h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m in as good stead for the one as the other.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with that other part of your Book, in examining what you say against the Assemblies Petition. Of which Petition I must adde this for a close, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that I can find in it, but is fully consonant to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples both of the Presbyterian, and the Congregationall way: and what you alledge against it, is equally destructive to both.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>